Guide to the Basil Lee Whitener Papers, 1889-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Basil Lee Whitener papers 1889-1968
whitener
Whitener, Basil Lee, 1915-
150 linear feet Extent: circa 297,300 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Basil Lee Whitener (1915-1989) was a U.S. Representative from Gastonia, N.C. Collection includes correspondence between Whitener and his constituents, other congressmen, and government officials, legislative materials, drafts of bills, financial papers, speeches, invitations, printed material, clippings, photographs, and other papers, chiefly from congressional files (1957-1968), relating to issues of national importance during the 1960s, including the Vietnam War, crime legislation, gun control, riots, civil rights legislation, foreign aid, social security, and the Taft-Hartley Act. Correspondents include Sam Ervin, John F. Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Sargent Shriver, and Strom Thurmond.
RL.01374
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Whitener Papers were transferred from Belmont Abbey College in 1978.
Biographical Note
May 14, 1915 Born in York County, South Carolina.
1931 Graduated from Lowell High School.
1933 Graduated from Rutherford Junior College.
1933 - 1935 Student at University of South Carolina.
1937 Received LL. B. degree from Duke University.
Aug., 1937 Admitted to the North Carolina Bar and entered general practice in Gastonia, North Carolina.
1938 Organizer and first President, Gastonia Junior Chamber of Commerce.
1938 - 1940 Instructor of business law at Belmont Abbey College.
1940 - 1941 Vice President, North Carolina Junior Chamber of Commerce.
1941 Member of the North Carolina House of Representatives. Re-nominated in 1942, but resigned to enter the U. S. Navy.
1941 - 1942 President, North Carolina Junior Chamber of Commerce.
Sept. 26, 1942 Married Harriet Priscilla Morgan. Their children are John Morgan (1945), Laura Lee (1950), Basil Lee, Jr. (1952), and Barrett Simpson (1960).
Oct. 5, 1942 - Nov. 6, 1945 Served as gunnery officer in U. S. Navy during World War II, and was separated from service with the rank of Lieutenant USNR.
1946 Member, North Carolina General Statutes Commission.
1946 - 1956 Solicitor of the 14th Solicitorial District.
1946 - 1947 President, Young Democratic Clubs of North Carolina.
1947 - 1949 Member of Commission to Study Improvement of Administration of Justice.
1948 Delegate, Democratic National Convention.
1948 - 1949 Chairman, Speakers' Bureau, Young Democratic Clubs of America.
Nov., 1949 Permanent Chairman, Young Democratic National Convention.
1949 - 1951 Chairman of Advisory Committee of Young Democratic Clubs of America.
1950 President of Gaston County Bar Association.
1951 Chairman of the Board of Regional Directors of the Young Democratic Clubs of America.
1957 - 1968 Elected to the 85th - 87th Congresses as Representative for the Eleventh District of North Carolina, and to the 88th - 90th Congresses as Representative for the Tenth District of North Carolina.
June 4, 1959 Admitted to District of Columbia Bar.
1960 Delegate, Democratic National Convention. Honorary LL. D. degree from Belmont Abbey College.
1965 Honorary LL. D. degree from Pfeiffer College.
1968 Returned to the practice of law in Gastonia, North Carolina.
Committee Assignments
Commmittee on Veteran's Affairs (Jan. 3, 1957 - Jan. 16, 1958)
Committee on the District of Columbia (87th Congress, 1st Session, 1961 - 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968)
Special Subcommittee on Metropolitan Police Department, Chairman
Special Subcommittee to Study Revenue Procedures in the District of Columbia, Chairman
Special Subcommittee on Traffic, Streets, and Highways, Chairman
Committee on the Judiciary (86th Congress, 1st Session, 1959 - 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968)
Special Subcommittee on State Taxation of Interstate Commerce, Appointed in 1961
In addition, Whitener served on several special committees investigating such matters as interstate taxation, the Chinese refugee problem, the International Police organization, and the International Court of Justice.
Collection Overview
Basil Lee Whitener Papers primarily contain the office files of Congressman Whitener when he was the U. S. Representative for the Eleventh District (85th - 87th Congresses) and Tenth District (88th -90th Congresses) of North Carolina. Although the papers span the years 1889-1968, the bulk of the papers covers Whitener's years in office, 1957-1968. Some of the early files from the 81st through the 84th Congresses, are the papers of Woodrow Wilson Jones, Whitener's predecessor in office.
luded in the papers are such Items as correspondence, printed material, invitations, speeches, clippings, financial papers, photographs, as well as legislative materials and drafts of bills. Much of this collection consists of correspondence between Whitener and his constituents, other Congressmen, and government officials.
The papers are divided into the following series:
Political
Correspondence (General)
Correspondence (Legislative)
District of Columbia
Judiciary
Judiciary Committee
Speeches
Subject
Case Files
Textile Imports
House of Representatives
Military and Veterans
Military Academy
Trips
Post Office
Grants
Invitations
General Information
Office Files
Office Information
Personal
By far the largest category is the Correspondence (General), even though it was weeded extensively. The Correspondence (Legislative) Series is also rather large. Both of these series contain extensive correspondence with constituents. Other large series are the Personal Series, which pertains more directly to Whitener's private and unofficial affairs, and the Office Files Series, containing files which seem to have been in active use by Whitener's office staff at the time he left office.
There are information and opinions in the collection on a variety of issues of national importance during the 1960s. Included are the Vietnam War, civil rights legislation, riots, crime legislation, gun control, foreign aid, Social Security, and the Taft-Hartley Act. Other subjects are the U. S. Congress and various bills and laws. There are a variety of letters from prominent persons, such as John F. Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Sargent Shriver, Strom Thurmond, and Sam Ervin.
The views of Whitener on many national and state issues are revealed within the collection. He supported legislation to combat crime and civil disobedience, a strong national defense, and exerting every effort to bring the Vietnamese Conflict to a successful conclusion. The Congressman was opposed to civil rights legislation, deficit spending, foreign aid spending, and the proliferation of domestic and social programs. Concerning North Carolina issues, Whitener wanted restrictions on textile imports in order to protect jobs, and supported the concept of a balanced economy in the state. As a member of the Committee on the District of Columbia, he authored bills to curb the crime rate in the District of Columbia and a bill to establish a modern rail rapid transit system in the District. In general, Whitener seemed to exhibit the views of conservative Southern Democrats.
Specific subjects are noted in more detail in the inventory. There is some overlap of subjects among the series.
Note on Processing and Arrangement
The arrangement of the Whitener Papers has followed the system originally used by the Congressman's office as much as possible. The series were grouped by placing the more significant and larger series in the beginning. The Personal Series was placed at the end. Although the collection was usually left in the structure it had when it came to the library, many of the folders within the series were in various states of disorder. Rearrangement of the order of these folders was often necessary in order to create a logical organization, whether it be chronological, subject, or some other arrangement. Folder titles remain intact whenever possible, except when clarification was necessary.
Although categories do indicate the contents, headings are not always inclusive. For example, there may be information on a Social Security bill in the Correspondence (Legislative) Series. However, information on the same bill may be located in other series, such as the House of Representatives or Judiciary. Such folders were retained in their original files.
Weeding out of certain material was a necessary part of the cataloging process for the collection. Two series were discarded. They were: the File Cards Series, containing only names and addresses with no other notations; and the Appalachian State Graduates Series, including names and addresses of graduates in the Tenth Congressional District. Routine Items were eliminated from the collection, especially in the Correspondence (General) Series, Subject Series, Case Files Series, and Personal Series. Examples of such Items are individual Social Security claims, visa applications, routine correspondence, and duplicates In the Military and Veterans Series only the files for the letter "C" were retained, as well as a few small subject folders. The majority of the folders in the Military Academy Series was discarded because they were individual application materials and academic records of Whitener's appointees. The same procedures as above were followed for the routine Military and Veterans, and Military Academy files contained in the Office Files Series. For more specific information, see the individual descriptions of series in the inventory.
Subject and autograph cards have been prepared for the card catalog, but they are very selective. Subject entries were made for series level topics, and for those of folder headings, if of sufficient importance. Whenever a subject entry was made, other references in other categories are possible because it was not feasible to specifically cite all references to a topic. Autograph cards were made only for outstanding correspondents, especially those in the Correspondence (General) Series.
Subject Headings
Civil rights -- United States; Gun control -- United States; Legislators -- United States -- Records; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Social security -- Law and legislation -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- Law and legislation; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; Ervin, Sam J. (Sam Jones), 1896-1985; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-; Thurmond, Strom, 1902-
Contents of Collection
- Political Series, 1956-1966
  This series primarily concerns Whitener's first bid for Congress in 1956. He decided to run for Congress in January of that year when Woodrow W. Jones declined to run for re-election as the representative of the Eleventh Congressional District. Included is information on the campaign and two primaries, as well as on the election. The primaries were held on May 26 (Whitener/Gardner/Wells) and June 23 (Whitener/Gardner). In addition to the 1956 campaign material, there are precinct committee lists for 1960 and 1962, and material pertaining to the 1966 campaign.
  - Congressional File, 1956, Jan. - Apr. (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    Concerns Whitener's candidacy for Congress and plans for the campaign
  - Congressional Campaign Correspondence, 1956, Apr. - Juneand undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - BLW for Congress, 1956, Mar. - Juneand undated (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Congressional Campaign - Post-Campaign Correspondence, 1956, May - Oct. (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    Includes congratulatory letter upon Whitener's election as well as thank you's for support in the campaign.
  - Congressional Correspondence, 1956, Jan. - Nov. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Information in reference to Whitener's early duties as a Congressman and preparations for his new position.
  - Congressional Correspondence, 1956, Dec.and undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Same as above.
  - Congressional Campaign Lists, 1956, Mar.- 1958, Oct.and undated (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    Also includes some correspondence.
  - Congressional Campaign Bills, 1956, Mar. - Aug.and undated (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Precinct Committee Lists,1960and1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Smyre Letter,1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Smyre was the Finance Chairman for the 1966 Whitener campaign for re-election.
- Correspondence (General) Series, 1956-1968
  This series, the largest in the collection, runs from the 85th Congress, first session, 1957, through the 90th Congress, second session, 1968. Included is correspondence to and from Whitener's constituents. Some of the letters were written by his administrative assistant, Herbert M. Lineberger. The papers are organized by Congress and session, and then alphabetically within each session by name of correspondent. In some cases Whitener's office held material together about a certain person in the folder for the letter of the alphabet for his name, regardless of the correspondents involved. For example, there may be letters about Mr. Capps in the C folder, which were written by various persons. There are a few subject folders included in the alphabetical arrangement. Items within the folders are filed chronologically.
  In addition to constituent mail, Whitener corresponded with prominent persons. Representative people are Sam Ervin, Thad Eure, Orville Freeman, Luther Hodges, J. Edgar Hoover, Hubert Humphrey, Lyndon Johnson, B. Everett Jordan, John F. Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Dan K. Moore, Admiral Hyman Rickover, Terry Sanford, Sargent Shriver, and Strom Thurmond. Several letters appear in this series for each of the above correspondents. Please consult the Autograph File of the card catalog for a detailed listing of these letters.
  A variety of topics appear throughout the series. Particularly in the late 1960s the themes of the Vietnam War, civil rights legislation, riots, crime legislation, gun control, and foreign aid appear often in constituent's letters. In 1968 some constituents were urging Whitener to run for governor of North Carolina. The papers go primarily through October, 1968.
  Extensive, although conservative, weeding was done in this series. The decision to weed was made because of the large proportion of routine material included. Approximately one-third of this series was discarded. The following is a list of the types of Items that were weeded out:
  1. Claims for individual Social Security benefits
  2. Passport and visa applications
  3. Individual immigration change of status requests
  4. Requests for prison paroles
  5. Routine congratulatory letters, except from prominent persons
  6. Routine job applications and resumes
  7. Correspondence concerning visits of school groups to Washington
  8. Expressions of sympathy
  9. Congratulations to new parents
  10. Welcome letters to new residents of Gastonia, N. C.
  11. Routine requests for government publications, flags, photographs, etc.
  12. Admissions of individual patients to hospitals and rehabilitation facilities
  13. Recalls and discharges from military service
  14. Individual income tax returns
  15. Tickets for athletic events
  16. Applications for individual Farmers Home Administration (FHA) loans
  17. Applications for enlistments and discharges from various branches of the military
  18. Duplicate copies of speeches, reports, memoranda, etc.
  - 85th Congress, 1st Session, 1957
    - A - G (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
    - H - P (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - R - S (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Speech at Dallas High School (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - T - Z (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
  - 85th Congress, 2nd Session, 1958
    - A - D (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - E - L (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - Mc - R (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
    - S - Z (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
  - 86th Congress, 1st Session, 1959
    - A - D (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
    - E - Mc (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
    - M - V (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
    - W - Z (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters Whitener wrote from his district office in Gastonia, N. C., and letters his administrative assistant wrote from the Washington office in his absence. (Box 14, Folder 4-7)
  - 86th Congress, 2nd Session, 1960
    - A - C (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
    - D - H (1960, Jan. - June) (Box 16, Folder 1-8)
    - H (1960, July- Dec.) - M (Box 17, Folder 1-7)
    - N - S (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
    - T - Z (Box 19, Folder 1-5)
    - Primarily letters Whitener wrote from his district office in Gastonia, N. C. (Box 20, Folder 1-7)
  - 87th Congress, 1st Session, 1961
    - A - C (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
    - D - H (1961, Jan. - Apr.) (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
    - H (1961, May - Dec.)- L (1961, Jan. - May) (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
    - L (1961, June - Dec.)- Q (Box 24, Folder 1-7)
    - R - S (Box 25, Folder 1-4)
    - Supreme Court (Admission of Attorneys, June 12, 1961) (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - T (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
    - U - Z (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
    - Primarily letters Whitener wrote from his district office in Gastonia, N.C., and letters his administrative assistant wrote from the Washington office in his absence. (Box 26, Folder 5-9)
  - 87th Congress, 2nd Session, 1962
    - A - C (1962, Jan. - Mar.) (Box 27, Folder 1-7)
    - C (1962, Apr. - Dec.)- F (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
    - G - J (Box 29, Folder 1-7)
    - K - M (1962, Jan. - July) (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
    - M (1962, Aug. - Dec.)- R (Box 31, Folder 1-8)
    - S - Z (Box 32, Folder 1-7)
  - 88th Congress, 1st Session, 1963
    - A - C (1963, Jan. - June) (Box 33, Folder 1-7)
    - C (1963, July - Dec.)- F (Box 34, Folder 1-7)
    - G - K and Knight, Douglas (Dinner) (Box 35, Folder 1-8)
    - L - N (Box 36, Folder 1-7)
    - O - S (1963, Jan. - Apr.) (Box 37, Folder 1-8)
  - 88th Congress, 1st Session, 1963
    - S (1963, May- Dec.) (Box 38, Folder 1-2)
    - Supreme Court - Admission of Attorneys (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - T - V (Box 38, Folder 4-5)
    - W - Z (Box 39, Folder 1-3)
  - 88th Congress, 2nd Session, 1964
    - A - C (1964, Jan. - Sept.) (Box 40, Folder 1-7)
    - C (1964, Oct. - Dec.)- G (Box 41, Folder 1-8)
    - H - K (Box 42, Folder 1-7)
    - L (Box 43, Folder 1-2)
    - Lowell, N.C. (1964-1967) (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and other papers concerning the application by the town of Lowell, N.C., for a federal grant in the amount of $246,548 to be used in the construction of a waste treatment plant.
    - Mc - N (Box 43, Folder 4-8)
    - O - S (1964, Jan. - May) (Box 44, Folder 1-7)
    - S (1964, June- Dec.) - Z (Box 45, Folder 1-8)
  - 89th Congress, 1st Session, 1965
    - A - B (Box 46, Folder 1-6)
    - C - E (Box 47, Folder 1-5)
    - F - H (1965, Jan. - May) (Box 48, Folder 1-6)
    - H (1965, June- Dec.) - L (Box 49, Folder 1-7)
    - Mc - Q (Box 50, Folder 1-7)
    - R - T (Box 51, Folder 1-7)
    - V - Z (Box 52, Folder 1-5)
  - 89th Congress, 2nd Session, 1966
    - A - B (Box 53, Folder 1-5)
    - Brown, Eugene R.: P.A.C.E., Inc. (Plan Assuring College Education in North Carolina) (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - C - D (1966, Jan. - Aug.) (Box 54, Folder 1-6)
    - D (1966, Sept. - Dec.)- G (Box 55, Folder 1-6)
    - H - J (Box 56, Folder 1-7)
    - K - M (1966, Jan. - Apr.) (Box 57, Folder 1-5)
    - M (1966, May- Dec.) - P (Box 58, Folder 1-6)
    - Q - S (1966, Jan. - Aug.) (Box 59, Folder 1-6)
    - S (1966, Sept. - Dec.)- V (Box 60, Folder 1-5)
    - W (Box 61, Folder 1-3)
    - Wright, M. A. (Box 61, Folder 4)
      Concerns an expression of interest in the improvement of Highway 105 in the Linville Falls area.
    - X - Z (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Primarily copies of letters written by Whitener from his Gastonia office, Oct. - Dec.,1966 (Box 61, Folder 6-7)
  - 90th Congress, 1st Session, 1967
    - A - B (1967, Jan. - July) (Box 62, Folder 1-5)
    - B (1967, Aug. - Dec.)- C (Box 63, Folder 1-6)
    - D - G (1967, Jan. - Apr.) (Box 64, Folder 1-6)
    - G (1967, May - Dec.)- H (1967, Jan. - Sept.) (Box 65, Folder 1-6)
    - H (1967, Oct. - Dec.)- L (Box 66, Folder 1-6)
    - Mc - N (Box 67, Folder 1-6)
    - O - R (Box 68, Folder 1-7)
    - S - T (Box 69, Folder 1-6)
    - U - Z (Box 70, Folder 1-6)
  - 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968
    - A - B (Box 71, Folder 1-3)
    - Boiling Springs, N.C.: Pollution Abatement Project (Folder includes supporting documents dating back to1961) (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - C (1968, Jan. - June) (Box 71, Folder 5-6)
    - C (1968, July- Dec.) - D (Box 72, Folder 1-4)
    - Dixon, Jeane, Luncheon (Box 72, Folder 5)
      Papers concerning a luncheon benefit for Holy Angels Nurseryin Gastonia, N.C. Mrs. Dixon was the honored guest at the affair on October 13,1968,and also spoke at a meeting that evening.
    - E - F (Box 72, Folder 6-8)
    - G (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Grants (Box 73, Folder 2-3)
      Announcements and correspondence concerning federal grants to colleges, cities, and counties in Whitener's district for various projects.
    - H (1968, Jan. - Aug.) (Box 73, Folder 4-6)
    - H (1968, Sept. - Oct.)- L (Box 74, Folder 1-7)
    - Mc - O (Box 75, Folder 1-6)
    - P - S (1968, Apr. - May) (Box 76, Folder 1-7)
    - S (1968, June- Aug.) - T (Box 77, Folder 1-4)
    - Telegrams (Box 77, Folder 5)
      Many of the telegrams relate to announcements of federal grants to various North Carolina cities and counties for such projects as water and sewer facilities, recreation, urban planning assistance, and college improvements. Whitener often mailed the telegram to the news media as well as to the party involved.
    - U - Z (Box 78, Folder 1-6)
    - Box 307 includes Items filed chronologically which have been pulled from throughout this category. A note has been made on each folder from which oversize Items were removed. Items such as printed material, newspaper clippings, a map, petition, and broadsides comprise this section (4 folders total). (Box 307, Folder 1-4)
- Correspondence (Legislative) Series, 1956-1968
  Like the Correspondence (General) Series, this series begins with the 85th Congress, first Session, 1957, and ends with the 90th Congress, second Session, 1968. Included is correspondence to and from Whitener's constituents that centers on legislation being considered in the House of Representatives. Some of the letters were written by his administrative assistant, Herbert M. Lineberger. The papers are organized by Congress and session, and then alphabetically within each session by name of correspondent. Items within the folders are filed chronologically. There are a few subject folders included in the alphabetical arrangement on such topics as the Taft-Hartley Act, Civil Rights Act of 1964, Social Security, the Food and Agriculture Act of 1962, etc. A variety of topics appear throughout the series. Examples of topics that surface in constituent's letters are the Landrum-Griffin Act (labor reform bill), veterans' legislation, foreign aid bill, prayer in schools, etc.
  - 85th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1957-1958
    - A - C (Box 79, Folder 1-5)
    - D - G (Box 80, Folder 1-4)
    - GI Housing and Loan Funds (H.R. 9744) (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - H - K (Box 80, Folder 6-10)
    - L - R (Box 81, Folder 1-9)
    - Radio, Daytime Broadcasting Stations; Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act; Republican County Organizations; Roxy Theatre (Box 82, Folder 1-5)
    - S (Box 82, Folder 6-7)
    - School Integration; Shelby Recruitment Program (Box 82, Folder 8-9)